[Music]
so
full
[Music]
so
hello hello everybody welcome to the
latest episode of the ask widget show
i hope you are all doing very well
uh today is a live chat
uh
episode which means i will be taking
questions only from the live chat this
is something i'm not done in several
months
so let's do that again but before we do
that let's see who all is there with us
i can see dharmel vladimir adityanath
that name always makes me smile
vladimir
uh
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you i hope you're
doing very well
so with that done
let us take some questions from the live
chat who all is there in the live chat
and what are the questions
how about this question so today let's
deal with something other than
geopolitics and history we can do some
history also but tomorrow is going to be
the geopolitics session so let's take
some other questions today for instance
this one
anirudh says what's your view on the use
of psychedelics
like dmt and their significance in human
life
uh well i personally have no experience
with psychedelics like dmt or any other
psychedelics but it's an interesting
thing
psychedelics induce certain mental
states in a person's mind psychedelics
like dmt i don't i don't remember the
full form of dmt
uh
there are things like cannabis
and various other psychedelics as well
these are all natural plant-based herbal
psychedelics that we're talking about uh
cylo cybin mushrooms also so these
induce various kinds of altered states
of consciousness in the human mind
you're in some kind of trance or you're
in some kind of parallel world you see
visions
you hear things that may not
exist in the real world and that sort of
thing and some people most people
apparently have good experiences with
dmt with silos in mushrooms uh even with
something like ayahuasca which uh people
in uh
which the native people of uh south in
various parts of south america they use
that and so on and some people have bad
experiences but some those are
in a small minority i believe
uh so i personally have from my own
perspective i don't know how it is i i
know people who have
experienced this
and in some cases it's a life-changing
experience
it's like you finally connect with
another world another realm and it it
gives some people
what seems to be the what seems to them
to be the proof that there is a world
beyond our own and maybe god exists and
spirits exist and all that
that sort of thing and it's something
that people have used for centuries for
thousands of years you know
various native peoples even in india we
had something called soma which we seem
to have lost i don't think it was a
psychedelic most likely soma was a
stimulant something that pumps you up
like like you know in gym people who
work out they use this these pre-workout
supplements it pumps you up and primes
you for having a heavy lifting in the
gym so soma seems to have been some kind
of stimulant that that warriors would
ingest before going into battle it would
make them you know
almost invincible
and there are lots of hymns to soma in
the rigveda and various other vedas but
so i don't think it was a psychedelic
because if you had an altered state of
consciousness
then maybe you would not do very well in
battle you know
so uh soma most likely was not a
psychedelic but you have things like uh
cylo cybin mushrooms that are found in
abundance apparently in india and you
have things like cannabis which is what
is colloquially known as ganja
ganja right
so cannabis is just a leaf it's it's a
herb it's a plant
and it's been used since time immemorial
by various uh
by by indians uh there are various uh
sadhus you know various
the classes of sadhus that use this
especially those who are
some of them who worship lord shiva they
they take it as part of their rituals
and all that so it's been there it's
been around in in humanity since
essentially since time times immemorial
it's always been a part of human
existence i'm not sure that everybody
partook of these experiences but
certainly it was something that was
accepted in in society especially indian
society it was not something that was
frowned upon it was not seen as
something that is illegal nowadays some
of these things are illegal i think when
it comes to ganja which is cannabis it's
kind of quasi-legal or quasi-illegal i
mean i don't think the cops especially
uh
go after people who use that even in
some festivals it's kind of more or less
legal people can use it openly and so on
so yeah it's been around for for the for
the longest period of time i think it
must be as old as humanity
and it would have
various
possibly positive effects on human
beings nowadays people use it in the
west in the u.s and
netherlands and other places
as a pain reliever some people who have
chronic illnesses or even terminal
illnesses like terminal cancer they use
cannabis
which kind of gives them some relaxation
and pain relief so these properties have
been known for a very long time and i
don't think cannabis is something that
is a habit-forming substance i may be
wrong don't quote me on that as far as i
know from my limited knowledge and
understanding cannabis doesn't seem to
be something that is habit-forming like
tobacco for instance tobacco is is like
a hard drug it's it's more addictive
than heroin and cocaine i mean people
who uh
are addicted to smoking or tobacco in
whatever form they find it
harder to quit the habit then heroin and
cocaine
addicts find
to quit heroin and cocaine so tobacco is
is really bad it's really really hard
for addicts to quit tobacco which is why
i have i have the highest respect for
those who have been
been tobacco addicts and then they gave
it up you know
so yeah so i don't think these
psychedelics are especially harmful
uh and i don't think that even if if you
if you smoke cannabis for instance
you're going to inhale dust i mean uh
soot and smoke into your lungs that will
obviously not have a very good effect
but i don't think it's anywhere as
harmful as inhaling tobacco smoke for
instance so overall i think cannabis and
cylosine mushrooms and ayahuasca and
whatever else dmt etc
these don't seem to have any genuinely
significantly harmful effects dmt is
something that seems to be especially
potent and powerful it's like taking a
shortcut into meditation when you
meditate
you go into altered states of
consciousness uh you actually
come into contact with your subconscious
when you your
practice of meditation is advanced
enough and you continue that for months
or years you may actually experience
visions you may see visions you may hear
things which
which others won't hear
so that's an advanced stage of
meditation
when you take something like dmt it kind
of acts it seems to act like a shortcut
to that advanced stage of meditation so
you may experience things like that but
it doesn't mean that you have become an
evolved more evolved human being the way
somebody who is an experienced meditator
would be right
so yeah it does give you certain
benefits it may be a life-changing
experience for many people i personally
have never experienced it but yeah it's
it's been around for the longest time
and
clearly it's never been seen as
something bad
right let's do something else uh let's
take some other questions so i saw
something interesting and it disappeared
very quickly
ron says i quit smoking for five months
and i don't feel eager to have it like i
used to have before first month is very
hard but once you can overcome that time
it gets steadily it goes down well
congratulations rohan and
respect to you sir for quitting tobacco
and please don't ever do it again
because it's not good we all know that
yeah so yeah i'm sure that the first
initial phase is the toughest the first
day the first week the first month and
it always gets better after that so
i'm very happy to see that you've quit
smoking and please
stay on track don't smoke again
okay let's take something else um
they just says why do you always call
pakistan a temporary nation and why not
bangladesh and sri lanka well bangladesh
vangadesh has always been known as
bangladesh
west bengal is actually
the bangladesh itself bangladesh
has been bifurcated partitioned into two
about more than 100 years ago by the
british
and the outcome of that is bangladesh
and west bengal so this region has
always been known as either gowda or
vanga or initially anger
right
so the name bangladesh makes sense it is
the correct name for the region and in
in the future we may in the long run
perhaps in 100 years maybe reincorporate
that within
greater india it is a likelihood a very
strong likelihood
so it is
something that will be re-incorporated
into india it will still be called
vanguard or whatever we want to call it
so that name is not temporary
as a nation it may exist for some time
yeah
and when it comes to lanka sri lanka
it's always been lanka for the longest
time for millennia
and it may be a nation it may be a
province it may be whatever but it's
always going to be lanka and that's why
i have never ever imagined calling sri
lanka temporary nation or bangladesh
temporary nation bangladesh is more
temporary
as it's as it would be because it's
always been
part of india sri lanka has been always
kind of detached for the past 10 000 or
so years because of the uh
because the ice age ended in the sea
levels rose so it became separated from
india but pakistan was
purpose
made
purposefully created for the sake of
destabilizing india the british did that
the british created pakistan
in order to keep india destabilized in
order to further their geopolitical
interests in the region
not only in asia not only in the indian
subcontinent but also in the gulf region
in the uh arabian subcontinent in the
arabian peninsula and so on so that wa
so
pakistan will last as long as these
nations as long as the west and china
for now
are in the ascendancy in our
on balance stronger than india as india
gets stronger it's pakistan will be
dealt with appropriately and that's why
the major focus has always been in
pakistan the major pain point for india
in the indian subcontinent is not
bangladesh by any means it's not sri
lanka by any means it's always been
pakistan
it's been created purposefully to keep
on destabilizing india to keep on
bleeding india and that's why that is
the first
uh matter that will have to be dealt
with by india geopolitically sri lanka i
have no issue if it stays a separate
nation nation state for the next 100 200
years whatever
they are anyway part of our civilization
we have nothing no friction with them no
no significant friction with them
yes right now they have various
puppet regimes that are essentially
puppets of the west and they are right
now the nation is being
compromised the economy has been
compromised by the west the imf loans
and all that we know how that works yeah
but sri lanka
culturally and people-to-people-wise
there is no real genuine friction and
that's why
we we are perfectly happy with sri lanka
the way it is bangladesh there are
issues but we will deal with them in in
a civilized
manner which is which is going to be
good for
the long-term interests of the peoples
of the uh
of the region and so on
pakistan also i don't i don't really uh
wish the people ill i genuinely have no
ill feeling for the people the common
man woman and child of pakistan i wish
them well i wish them happiness i wish
them long-term prosperity but the
nation-state is
an abomination it has been created for
the sake of destabilizing india it has
to be dealt with geopolitically
at the right time at the right time in
the right way so that's why because of
these reasons i mean you could even say
afghanistan has been carved out of india
by foreign colonizers
which happened in the past 1000 years so
yeah so that also you could say it's
it's unfinished business in a way yeah
but let's let's uh look at the most
immediate
and most pressing matter which is
pakistan so that's why i i have never
even imagined
calling afghanistan or
or bangladesh or sri lanka temple
relation i
i only
wish to deal with pakistan first and
that's what we will do yeah so
that's the reason yeah i hope it makes
some sense
okay let us see some other questions
uh afghanistan and pakistan both
afghanistan and pakistan need to be
incorporated into india i would disagree
i mean i don't know which time frame
you're looking at if you're saying we
need to incorporate afghanistan pakistan
into india the next 20 years good god no
thank you
have you seen the kind of people there
are
who live there the overall outlook
see
there was a pew pew poll done in
afghanistan
before the americans withdrew
uh some time ago
and according to that pupil over 90 of
the people who responded to the poll
expressed a desire for afghanistan to be
a sharia state right so that is
the will of the people of afghanistan is
that compatible with the uh will of the
people of india and the culture of india
does does that mix it doesn't mix and
therefore it's
pointless and completely
counterproductive to even think of
incorporating afghanistan into india
right now yeah maybe
in the future and when we talk about the
future we're talking about our
descendants will do that maybe 100 years
from now or so yeah not now and
similarly pakistan also has a very has
an even
i mean afghanistan the people of
afghanistan still have some kind of
warmth towards india they they don't see
india as an elimination the people of
pakistan are
brainwashed
since
nursery and junior cajun senior cajun
first handed into hating india
can you really incorporate those people
back into india just imagine
how things will go if we do that if we
inco reincorporate pakistan the the
territory into india and open the
borders just imagine the situation that
will create can't do that right now
so there will be other ways of dealing
with pakistan first of all we need to
deal with the army
that has this strangle hold and choke
hold on the people and the resources
of this territory
currently presently temporarily pakistan
then give it some time to settle down
let pashtunistan the northwest parts of
the northwest frontier province and
khaibar pakhtunwa let that go back let
that reunite
with the nation of afghanistan because
that obviously is uh makes sense yeah
from an ethnic and cultural and
linguistic perspective
let
synth become free for some time let
balochistan go its own way for some time
yeah and let's push the punjab also deal
with its people for some time and then
in the long run we will do whatever is
appropriate slowly slowly suddenly yeah
patience my friends patience not yet
okay
um
let us see ah yeah okay we should always
take a couple of questions about aliens
yeah are aliens real pentagon said they
they have more videos of the ufos but
they won't publish them is it true
listen i have never met an alien i have
never seen any unequal unequivocal
evidence of aliens existing all you see
is this renews reports in these grainy
videos and grainy photographs which
doesn't prove anything and which
actually makes me more skeptical yeah so
i believe that
the universe is so vast that aliens
other intelligent
civilizations other than ours would
certainly exist i am almost 99.999
convinced that they exist somewhere
maybe in our own galaxy maybe in other
galaxies but have they ever come to the
to our planet there is no evidence for
that no evidence as far i have not found
any evidence that is hundred percent
conclusive and proves it beyond a doubt
there are
pieces of circumstantial evidence that
may look like this may look like that
but it doesn't convince me completely so
therefore
as far as i'm concerned there is no
proof
there is no unequivocal proof of aliens
i would love if they were there i would
certainly want to have an alien sitting
next to me how are you doing sir and
let's have a conversation yeah but until
that's possible i will say no
the day i have an alien sitting here
we're gonna have fun
not yet it's too early for that too
early for that my friends
okay shivam says why did the indian
people lose the ability to read the
brahmi and gupta period scripts until
the god damn brits deciphered them in
the 19th century you see things change
if you want to understand the world in
two words
it is
things change
the world changes
okay
and
lots and lots of scripts
have evolved naturally over time in
india
you had the saraswati era
which which seems to have been
deciphered yeah recently and the
disarmament seems to make sense so the
saraswati sindhu era script then you
have a later
uh evolution of that which seems to be
the transitive brahmi script which seems
to have
emerged around 1500 bc
then you had the proper brahma script
then you had also something called
karoshi now you have the brahmi script
and then you have a whole bunch of
scripts
that come out of brahmi so brahmi
evolved into a whole family
of different scripts and as these new
scripts emerged
the people wherever these scripts
emailed the people started using those
scripts in overtime the scripts evolved
more and more and became more and more
different from the parent brahmi script
so after a thousand years after 1500
years people kind of lost the ability
to read brahmi but if you examine
the morphology of the brahmi characters
and you compare that with these similar
characters with the same sounds
in various descendant scripts you can
actually see that yeah i can see how it
evolved
yeah so because of the passage of time
and because of the adoption of the
daughter scripts of brahmi that's why
people lost the ability to
read the parent script the british
deciphered the script if the british had
not done it we would have done it
so let's not give undue
credit to the british for doing
everything good in india they've done
nothing good in india anyway that's a
whole different story let's not go there
for now so that's why this happened
but i mean even the gupta period script
is
a script that has emerged out of brahmay
various south east asian scripts like
the khmer script like the mons crypto
the thai script like the burmese script
etc are also scripts that are
descendants daughter scripts of the
parent brahmi script and so on so forth
all right so i hope that uh
answers
this question
i speak five languages says rakshit and
i am interested in learning linguistics
how to go about it
you speak five languages you're
interested in learning linguists i'm not
sure if there are any text books on
linguistics etc and so on
um
i think the more
languages you are exposed to the more
connections and patterns you're able to
see
and if you speak five indian languages
you essentially essentially is speaking
languages that are very closely related
to each other let's say you speak
hindi
odiya
kannada
and telugu
these
four languages are very closely related
to related to each other
about 40 to 50 of the vocabulary of
these four languages will be the same
so it's actually various dialects and
very closely related languages to to the
uh
so that's how it is but if you
learn
a language that may be part of the same
language family but it's a further away
language let's say you learn irish
garlic
or let's say you learn the catalan
language
or let's say you learn the
language of the faroe islands or you
learn german
or you learn italian
then you're going to see similarities
and patterns that are very far apart but
you can still say this america so i
think
practical linguistics is lies in
learning more languages
you also can learn linguistics formally
you have to learn the stuff morphology
of the phonemes and all that stuff yeah
so for that i'm sure there are textbooks
i have never studied linguistics from a
textbook my understanding of linguistics
comes because i have
been exposed to a variety of
indo-european languages
i
uh
from childhood i was exposed because of
school to sanskrit then i know at least
two three different indian languages i
also know a couple of foreign languages
western languages i also have a little
bit of exposure to latin and so on and
that's why i'm able to
that's why i was able to uh see all the
patterns that that
underlie the indo-european languages but
i have never studied linguistics
formally in in a in a classroom setting
from a textbook and all so i suppose
there must be textbooks for that i mean
you should you can look it up and start
studying yeah that's what i would say
how to go about studying something first
of all acquire the fundamentals the
textbooks that elucidate the
fundamentals
start with the most basic textbooks
master that study that's spent six
months one year studying that mastering
that and then go on to more advanced
textbooks that's how you learn anything
so that's what i would uh
tell you
to do
right
all right all right uh i think i took
the question last week what are your
views on india having a nationwide
morning in reaction to the death of the
queen of england however 15th august
modiji made a speech on removing
colonial thinking
was there a nationwide mourning
in reaction to elizabeth's death
i did not observe a single human being
or non-human being
mourning anything
i saw people having fun
the the official day of morning was last
sunday i believe i think people were
having fun last sunday i didn't
observe a single person wearing morning
clothes and shedding tears
and not you know
all that
i observed lots of people having a lot
of fun i did not observe a single person
was upset or morning so this was a
symbolic gesture that the government did
on a sunday
when no banks are open and even if it
was not on sunday there was there was
going to be no bank holiday or anything
it was a purely symbolic gesture now the
question you're asking is about removing
colonial thinking
mr modi modi ji said this
he said that we need to eradicate all
traces of colonial of mental
colonization and
visible colonization from india
by 2047
right it's a process that happens step
by step the key to doing that is to
change the education system
we are not even taught what the
colonizers did to us and that's why we
keep blaming ourselves for everything
that's wrong in indian society
right so these things will take time
it's going to be a step by step process
we have done some symbolic things and
more than symbolic things we have
changed the naval enzyme of the indian
navy they have removed that abominable
cross
yeah the foreign cross which has nothing
to do with india or indian history or
indian culture it is a symbol
and a and a visible sign of colonization
of end of slavery so we have removed
that symbol which is a great step it is
more than a symbolic gesture we have
also uh placed the statue of
nithyanandas where the statue of the
king of england needs to stand excellent
again so and we have renamed the rajpath
which was named in honor of the british
king to uh karthavya mark or something
like that right
i think something like that
so it is a process
steps are being taken
very do you know that in in various
commonwealth nations there was
a significant
uh period of mourning and very visible
morning and genuine morning
unlike in india where it was only in
name
so
we are still
part of the commonwealth we are still
not a nation
that is that powerful that we can just
shake everything off like the us did the
us was also ruled by the british
remember that but they fought the
british
on the battlefield in battlefields and
they defeated the british
comprehensively and they evicted them
threw them out
and by means of doing this because they
did that they had earned the right to
not be part of the commonwealth has
india earned the right to not be part of
the commonwealth we are still mentally
colonized we are still overly colonized
in so many things so it's going to be a
process
it's not going to happen today
please understand everything is a
process it has to happen step by step
it is something called phased deployment
it will happen by 2047 and the process
is now accelerating
so you all need to contribute to the
acceleration if if
you can see any any signs and symbols of
colonization do not respect that do not
pay tribute to that and first of all
mentally decolonize yourselves my dear
friends so that's how we do it
all right
um
harsh says what's your view regarding
the re-introduction of the cheetah meow
and how is it going to help our ecology
do you all know what sound a cheetah
makes
do you think cheetahs roar like lions in
leopards
well i i would say
i would i would encourage you to watch
youtube videos of kita's vocalizing they
meow like cats
and yet there are no cats there are no
house cats they are big creatures and
they can
easily dismantle a human being should
they be so inclined anyhow the question
is about the reintroduction of the
cheetah so uh was it today was it
yesterday i think it was yesterday or
today uh the prime minister uh
officially introduced those cheetahs
those eight seven eight nine whatever
the number is cheetahs that we have
brought in from namibia and they have
been reintroduced into the wild in india
for the first time in nearly a century
we have cheetahs on indian territory
fantastic
so what's my view about this it's it's a
it's been a long time coming and it's
great that we have finally done finally
done this
india had been requesting our
persian brethren ancestor and their
government
to send us some cheetahs the last
remaining population
of asiatic cheetahs
exists in persia in iran right
and that's the same species as the
subspecies the same subspecies as the
extinct indian cheetah
the the our persian
friends just kept on putting it off and
it's never happened yeah they acted very
very pricey
so now finally we have done this we have
brought in cheetahs from namibia
and apparently not apparently it has
been demonstrated that the uh
that the subspecies of cheetah that
lives in namibia is genetically quite
close to the extinct indian cheetah so
dr niraj rai and his team they did a
study a genetic study of the
mitochondrial dna of the
of a couple of specimens of indian
cheetahs from museums and a couple of
specimens of namibi namibian cheetahs
and they found that the namibian
subspecies is quite
close to the indian subspecies of
cheetah and that's why it makes sense to
reintroduce cheetahs from namibia rather
than from other parts of africa so
that's been done it's not about helping
our ecology uh
uh it's about re reintroducing an animal
that has been part of our our landscape
for thousands of years tens of thousands
of years right so it it makes sense to
have these animals back and eventually
what happens it will rebalance the the
ecosystem
every single species and subspecies of
animal whether it is insects whether it
is arthropods whether it is birds
whether it is animals herbivores
carnivores they all create a certain
balance in the ecosystem and the british
by eradicating the cheetah created an
imbalance in the ecosystem of india
which would have manifested itself in a
variety of ways unfortunately our
natural historians etc have published no
studies about the impact of the
extinction of the cheetah on the indian
ecosystem there is not a single study
that has been published as far as i have
seen and i've actually looked for this
what has been the effect long-term
effect and consequences of the
disappearance of the cheetah on the
overall ecosystem in india
flora and fauna and all that nothing has
been done there must have been a
significant effect yeah
because there will be species of of
creatures of animals that would be the
natural prey
for the cheetah and the cheetah would be
their natural predator predator and the
existence of both these species and on
classes of species would would
create a certain balance
in the ecosystem
and the disappearance of the predator
would have created an imbalance in terms
of an overpopulation of the species that
the cheetahs would typically prey upon
so these things would have happened but
no study has been done because our
scientists etc they i don't know what
they do
i have no idea what they do yeah anyhow
so the reintroduction of the cheetah
will rebalance the ecosystem it's just
seven or eight or nine two it's less
than ten i know
and it's gonna take time we would need
at least a few hundred cheetahs for this
rebalancing to actually take place
wherever the cheetahs are reintroduced
so it's still very early days we're
gonna give these cheetahs some time to
settle down right now their nerves will
be all shaken up because of the plane
journey yeah
and they are now in an unfamiliar
environment they were in namibia out
there in india
it will take them some time maybe a few
weeks to settle down
and then they can have a few offspring
will be born on indian soil that is a
great thing
and let this happen and maybe we can
bring in a few more cheetahs in the
future
and once we have a few hundred two at
least the same number as the indian
lions that we have in gujarat then we
could say that we can now study and see
the kind of rebalancing of the ecosystem
that that's happening before so until
that happens it's still very early days
it's still very early it's just a small
number of it's more like a symbolic
introduction but a very good and
positive and important step all right
right next question what other questions
do we have lost tribes of israel i have
no idea about that
um
gb says
is it true that the ming chinese had
discovered america and sailed around
africa in the 15th century before
columbus
as gavin menzies claimed aztec porcelain
cultural links and mitochondrial dna you
know this story of this great
chinese explorer called shanghai who
apparently was a eunuch whatever that
means
these stories started circulating in the
very
early years that of the 21st century
around the year
or the late part of the 20 of the 20th
century in the late 90s early 2000s
these stories started circulating and
the americans were at the forefront in
time magazine etc they started talking
about these stories
how much truth is there to it and how
much of it is propaganda i still can't
tell
i still can't tell how much of this
propaganda and how much of this is true
maybe some of it is true maybe this
fellow shanghai may have come to sri
lanka or something but there are stories
of of the chinese having gone all around
the universe maybe even to the moon and
jupiter and all
i don't know what's the evidence yeah
so
i am extremely skeptical about these
stories all right i'm very skeptical
about this
uh
and uh
i personally have seen no evidence that
the chinese had discovered america and
sailed around africa and all that there
are various claims that are made
i have not seen evidence that that
convinces me thus far so that's what i
would say
about this
matter
all right all right let's see some other
questions let's see some other questions
uh your take on play pm modi and
vladimir putin's dialogue at the seo
summit 2022 let more facts emerge what
what what was discussed and all but it's
good that the two leaders met
and had the conversation and i had a
discussion about various matters
uh
so that's what i can see from the
preliminary news reports that we have
seen i'm not sure what was detailed was
discussed in detail but i think it's a
positive move yeah it's a very positive
move
it's a great move and we need to keep
doing that
oh here we go
what is proto tami's
how does zh equal to l
how does it work
anyway let's not go there what is
prototyping
civilization is it really a thing
there is only one civilization which is
indian civilization which goes back 10
000 plus years now every time you
discover a new archaeological site you
will
observe that the media will term that as
a new civilization
so if you discover
next week
a new archaeological site in madhya
pradesh they will say madhya pradesh
civilization if you discover a new
archaeological site in
rajasthan they will say rajasthan
civilization if you discover something
new in maharashtra they will see a new
maharashtrian civilization
this is
nonsense they don't even know the
meaning of what of civilization
everything was interconnected
interrelated we have discovered so
little thus far because our
archaeologists
for whatever reason have been doing
nothing until very recently now we are
discovering new things yes we have
discovered the sites like kilady
and
adi challanur
and lots of other sites
so we are now going to start seeing the
interlinkages between these sites
and the sites in the rest of india i
mean you find
various variants of the brahmi script
there what does it mean
it means so this wasn't isolated from
northern and western india it was all
connected interconnected yeah so there
is no such thing as proto-tamil proto
something else proto this prototype that
proto-maharashtrian proto
proto kashmir it's just india
and this is something i've been trying
to say for the past more than one year
but um i'm sure there are people who
have come more recently in on this
channel but it's just indian
civilization
india is the first place
where the out of africa migrants
settled down permanently
and this settlement happened at least 74
000 years before today and since that
time indian culture and civilization has
been developing in a variety of ways
this is the oldest civilization and the
unmistakable evidence of cultural
continuity and civilizational continuity
goes back
at least 9500 years
and the more we explore archaeologically
the more the the older it's gonna get
because there are thousands of
unexplored archaeological sites
all across india there are thousands
just on the dry river bed of the extinct
saraswati river can you imagine how much
there is to discover
so there is no such thing as proto-tamil
something else or whatever it's just
indian civilization right please
understand that
okay who's the most fearsome warrior in
the whole of known history
who was the greatest warrior of the
mahabharata it was arjun right
arjun the great warrior part
the great part of the great gudakesh
so arjun was one of the most fearsome
warriors in who in the known in the
whole of history lord rama was one of
the greatest warriors of course who came
before
arjuna
uh lord bhima was a massively powerful
and and very very strong warrior almost
impossible to defeat
but
we don't quite know when these events
happened we have some tentative dates
but tentative date ranges
but even today most academics would say
that this is mythology right and they're
completely wrong about that anyhow when
we talk about
more grounded history where we actually
know the dates
who's the most fearsome warrior
well
so when you talk about the greek
achilles even that kind of seems like
mythology of course they did discover
the place which is considered to be troy
which is his harleque in anatolia in
western anatolia present-day turkey yeah
so achilles would have would have most
likely existed the greek warrior
achilles and he was the greatest warrior
of his time and the greatest warrior of
the trojan war yes so he's one of the
great warriors alexander was a great
conqueror who conquered all the way up
to the
last frontier which he could not conquer
which killed him which is india so he
was a great warrior yes napoleon was a
great warrior but if you wanted me to
name one person
in
known
in recorded history in
in the sense that we know the dates i
would say it would be the great shri
ching is khan
and his people i mean what he did nobody
else did he conquered more territory in
20 years than the roman emperors
conquered in 300 years
think about it
chung is khan
conquered more territory in 20 years
than all of the roman emperors conquered
in 300 years
and way more than alexander way more
than anybody else we know so if you want
to talk about the past three thousand
four thousand years
certainly as far as we know
it is the great
warrior the great uh freedom fighter and
and warrior for peace shri king is khan
he was somebody who fought for peace for
establishing peace and the rule of law
in the world all right so in my opinion
thus far as far as you know he's the
greatest
in the last four thousand years of
history
okay uh rathord rohit says why are we
not able to make our own jet engine
until now and we don't have any fifth
generation fighter jet we are in the
process of developing let me answer the
second half of the question first
we are
in the process
of developing at least one fifth
generation fighter jet which is the amca
advanced medium
combat aircraft amca there could be a t
e
t e d b f being developed a twin engine
deck based fighter which is something
that will live on
aircraft carriers
that most likely would be a fifth
generation fighter jet the amca is
definitely going to be a fifth
generation fighter jet with stealth
characteristics and various other
features and so on so forth so
because of the success of the pages
fighter jet program we now have the
industrial base and know how to make
better and better jet planes it's all
going to be based off the
learnings and the lessons learned during
the development of the pages fighter
plane which was a long process it was
still worth it
now we're gonna have more advanced
variants of the pages fighter plane and
we're gonna use these learnings for the
amc and other fighter planes and that
that development process is going to be
much faster and much more successful
because of the lessons we've run now jet
engines so even when it comes to the
amca the initial
prototypes and the first batch i suppose
will use an american engine
you know a general electric engine most
likely
so the question is why does it take so
long why is it taking so long to develop
a jet engine yeah
i mean we have a working coverage engine
but it's underpowered it's uh
the kind of thrust it generates is about
70 75 kilonewtons which is not enough
we want a jet engine that has 90 plus
kilo newtons of trust of thrust at least
maybe more than that i don't remember
the exact numbers but we want something
that's much more powerful now what is
the problem what's the problem why is it
so hard to develop jet engines the
chinese have been trying to develop a
jet engine of their own for the longest
time they seem i mean they claim to have
succeeded to some extent now to some
extent extent now the w something
jet engine or whatever it is
but it's still not a very reliable
engine so why is it so hard to develop
jet engines so let's go back to the
first initial days
when jet engines became a thing the
first jet engines
were developed by general german
scientists
during the second world war so the
entire concept of a jet engine came out
of germany the first jet engines were
placed
um
was the
i think it was an uh
german aircraft and what they've
discovered is that after one flight or
one sorority the jet engines were burned
out and you had to replace the jet
engines with a completely new set of
engines
so the thing is this
in a jet engine
you are
ingesting air from the front pulling it
and sucking it in
and then you are mixing that air with
the fuel you're burning it at extremely
high temperatures and that explosive
reaction of this high pressure air
mixing with
fuel and exploding
that
forms the thrust of the jet engine from
the back
that is a very high temperature and high
pressure reaction which tends to destroy
the turbine blades of a jet engine
so if you have a regular turbine blade
made out of your typical steel or
whatever metal you use it's going to
degrade very rapidly very very rapidly
and because of that
what the jet engine manufacturers have
to do is that they have to develop
exotic materials
when it comes to the successful jet
engines like rolls-royce and in the
saffron french engine and all that
various
makes of jet engine they typically
construct the turbine blades which is
the
most delicate component which needs to
be very tough they construct these
turbine blades as a single crystal of
metal
the entire blade
is grown
like you grow a plant or a tree it's
grown in its inch they ensure that it's
a single crystal of metal
that's what they do and
the exact substance they use the exact
metal or alloy they use
is
top secret
and this is something they have
perfected over several decades initially
all jet engines were highly unreliable
they would blow up or burn
and things would go bad
right so this is something that took
many minute decades for them to develop
and perfect
so india
also will have to go through that
process of trial and error and lots of
painful
you know
painful failures which we have gone
through when it comes to the coverage
engine so we have two options in front
of us
either we go through the whole tedious
long painful process until we have
a reliable
90 plus kilonewton engine or
we pay somebody some money and acquire
and buy the technology so most likely
the best candidate is france
they have this company called safha or
snikma i don't know what it's called
nowadays one of these two names and they
uh most likely are willing to
offer the technology at a price the
price is going to be really high they're
going to demand an arm and a leg for it
yeah and even then we have to ensure
that they are not cheating us and not
depriving us of some key components
so it's it's something that india will
have to approach very carefully to
ensure that we are getting our money's
worth
so it's something that seems to still be
in process or has something happened and
we don't know about it
maybe we should not know about it until
the time is right you'd never announce
a success
until it is a faith accompli until it's
done and sometimes even after you've
done it and even after you've
accomplished what you want to accomplish
you don't announce it to the world
in order to keep your adversaries and
enemies off we have no
offi there is no death of enemies for us
so we want to keep them guessing yeah so
um
so that's the reason why this jet engine
development takes so long it's so hard
the chinese are still struggling with
that and they have many much more
resources they can throw much more money
it's not about throwing money
you know it's about
going through the process of trial and
error and trial and error and do it
again and again and again until you
start seeing what works and then you
build up on that it's a long process
this is engineering
engineering is art and science together
it is science it it all works on the
basis of the principles and the laws of
physics
and yet there is an art to it there is
an art to it that's what engineering is
anybody who
manufactures things anybody who who
builds
stuff with their own hands with tools
knows that there is an art
to it in addition to the science behind
it so that's the process
developing a fighter jet is way easier
than developing a jet engine we already
have the some of the best missiles in
the world
we already have a very good um
rocket uh
ecosystem you know
a family of rockets we have the pslv we
have various kinds of jslv rockets
various variants
we have our own cryogenic engines we
have all the ingredients to build very
powerful rockets if the government
allows us it allows the allows this role
that's a different story so it's easier
to build cryogenic engines it's easier
to build
high quality rockets powerful rockets
it's easier to build jet planes than
building
a reliable
jet engine yeah so that's what it is
shall we take some video chat questions
i've not done that for a very long time
shall i do that yes no would you like to
come on video chat and maybe me take a
few questions from video
let's see if you all are willing maybe i
may think about it
later on
during this session
okay
harish says what's your views on esports
do you think it qualifies as a
legitimate sport
um
it is
well
i i don't know if it qualifies as a
legitimate small do i have a point of
comparison
take chess
in russia they consider chess to be a
real sport i think in most of the world
chess is recognized as a genuine
legitimate sport and at the highest
level
of chess at the grand master level of
chess at the top of the grand muscle
level when the best chess players in the
world they participate in let's say a
10-day or a week-long tournament and
they are playing chess matches chess
games every day at the highest level
typically over a week or two they lose
close to 10 kilos of weight that's how
much processing power their brain is
using you know the brain is the most
resource intensive organ in the human
body
and they
are processing data and calculating
moves
at such a high uh
level that it it it consumes so much
energy and they lose that energy in
terms of weight you know body weight so
yeah in a way it's it's a sport and i'm
not sure about esports how that is done
do you need that sort of mental focus
and processing in esports as well do
people who participate in esports
tournaments also come out all exhausted
and and
weight loss
not sure if that is the case then i i if
if that is something that indeed happens
if it is physically demanding
then i would say that it would be
something that is in some ways on par or
similar to chess in which case i would
say that we have a legitimate point of
comparison and then it makes sense to
classify esports as legitimate sports so
i
personally have not looked into this
but if you want to
find bases or basis of comparison that's
what i can offer to you and if it does
work that way then i would say that
maybe it should be considered to be a
legitimate sport
right
some people are saying they would like
to do video chat with me
all right we can perhaps consider that
we can personally consider that
says talk about the start and the
evolution of boxing
i think boxing has existed for millions
of years
do you know that kangaroos
can box
kangaroos have three legs
their tail is used at the leg that's
what i mean by that right
so they you they have a very massive
muscular tail
they can actually relax on that on their
tail and and
they have two
powerful hind legs and they're very
muscular tail so they use that as a
tripod that gives them extreme stability
and then they can box i've seen
kangaroos boxing and throwing punches at
humans you know i've seen that
so kangaroos box
i'm sure some dinosaurs would have
existed that would also have boxed and
we humans i mean i've seen chimpanzees
and gorillas throw punches just the way
a human being would do so i think boxing
has been around forever
the art of throwing a punch that's
something that comes naturally to all
human beings and to our closest
relatives the chimpanzees gorillas
orangutans i suppose they would also do
that forming a fist and throwing a punch
so i think boxing has been around
in that sense for the past 20 million
years the
thing of
forming a fist and throwing a punch but
the actual sport
well i think that would have been around
for about
a couple of centuries perhaps yeah
and it's evolved it's evolved so
if you look at the boxing champions the
heavyweight and other walking champions
of the early 20th century they look not
that physically impressive they're not
all chiseled right they they typically
are not very impressive physical
specimens they are definitely bulked up
and muscular and all but not the way
uh heavyweight boxes are today
so in the early 20th century you had
strong men who would box they would be
physically imposing but they would not
have the defined muscular physic that
would come in later even if you look at
one of the greatest heavyweight
champions of all time muhammad ali
you look at him he is not that well
built as let's say mike tyson or evander
holyfield right
he was lighter in weight actually
so boxing has evolved it's become more
demanding
more physically uh demanding yes more
more brutal in a sense
and then you you can see the pinnacle of
boxing in someone like mike tyson
that guy was a physical specimen i mean
if you see his punching speed and all
it's it's blinding
his punching speed was similar to the
punching speed of someone like bruce lee
for instance
that guy was i i would say the most
the scariest and most intimidating boxer
of all time would possibly be mike tyson
even scarier than muhammad ali
and today of course when it comes to
boxing uh you have someone like the
gypsy king
the gypsy king what's his name fury
tyson fury and he has a sibling also a
brother who also is a boxer
so tyson fury is the greatest boxer
today
and he thrice no twice defeated
what's his name the bronze bomber what
was his name deontay wilder he's also a
physical specimen if you look at tyson
fury he's not that impressive a physical
specimen he's very tall 610 or so but
he's a fat guy of sorts you know he
doesn't have that aesthetic physique but
he's a great boxer
so boxing has evolved and and when it
comes to lighter weights you have
someone like
what is his name um
mayweather floyd mayweather who never
lost a single mouth he was a technical
boxer he never looked for for knockouts
he just made sure he got that the
punches in and you know he goes he's
called the points and he had it down to
to us to
you know
he was the master of that he never lost
a single fight he recently retired and
then came out of retirement to to box
against what's his name uh the notorious
conor mcgregor and defeated him
and maybe he may still do that in the
future so he's made incredible amounts
of money out of boxing
so that's how it's been boxing at the
very high level highest level is a very
lucrative sport if you can box at a high
level you're going to make millions
especially in the west especially in the
u.s in india i don't know what the deal
is you know
but that's how it is
so it's it's a fun sport to watch it's
it's combat the the most
the most primal form of sport you know
one man against another man nowadays one
lady against another lady so it's about
two people
out there and you play by the rules and
you see who comes out on top
so yeah it's it's something that appeals
to most people as
unless you you have
an aversion to violence and and all that
i think it appeals
possibly to males more because males
have a
more of that tendency yeah
so yeah it's i've always enjoyed
watching boxing nowadays i also enjoy
watching mma mixed martial arts that's
also fun that is
even more primal and and more
you know of that than than boxing
so
combat smarts sports overall is
something that i have always enjoyed
watching never done it myself but yeah
all right all right some other questions
um
what else do we have do we have any
interesting question
any royal families left in india or all
of them wiped out no
there are lots of descendants of
erstwhile royal families in india
many of them would not even know perhaps
that they belong there their descendants
of whatever lineage
none of them have been actually
completely wiped out
what happened in 1857 is that many of
these genuine
kings
and rulers and queens some of them and
we know that yeah right running lecture
let me buy
they rose up
against the british
and there was this attempt the first war
of independence to evict these evil
brutal barbaric colonizers from india
this attempt failed
in the aftermath of the 1857 war of
independence the british systematically
destroyed every royal family either
during the warfare during the warfare or
later on
so what was done is that all of these
royal lineages were terminated most of
them were killed off the kings the
legitimate kings their extended families
would have stayed alive
it's impossible to trace everybody back
but yes the most important members of
the family would have been terminated
killed off yeah and then some
unimportant
distant relation
would be brought in and installed as a
puppet king or queen
and that gave rise to princely states
now some of the princely states were
actually
continuations of the legitimate royal
lineages
in some cases certain royal families
decided it wasn't it was
better
in their estimation to cooperate with
the british in some ways in order to
keep serving their people look at the
royal family of travancore they are
continuation of the older lineage
before 1857 and they have done the
greatest of service to their people by
never allowing the british to know how
much treasure was stored in the shri
padmanaba swami temple
these are people who did genuine service
to the nation even while pretending to
be
puppets of the british so they lost all
their power they had to
accept british political agents on their
territory they had to accept british
laws and rules
they had to accept all british demands
and they had to pay taxes to the british
and yet in some small way in some way
they kept on serving their people and
the nation and the civilization
there are many other royal families that
made this compromise because they had no
choice
so some royal families actually are a
continuation of older legitimate
lineages some are just puppets
and some are creations of the british
for instance the the nawabs of patodia
were created by the british
this this
institution of the namab of fatahdi was
created by the british in exchange for
services rendered to the british crown
so there was some some afghan
origin
afghan origin mercenary or something who
took the side of the british in some war
battle i don't know which one it was i
don't remember you can look it up look
it up look at that look it up yeah
and in exchange for these wonderful
services that he rendered to the british
they created
they created the institution of the
nawab of this small
uh bunch of villages the most prominent
of which was pataudi in haryana and
that's how this new institution of the
navajo portal was created so many of
these royal families are completely fake
many of them have been created by the
british many of them were terminated and
then replaced by puppets
which were distant relatives and some of
them were actual some of them that
existed are actual descendants of the
original
legitimate leading uses lineages
but in many cases you would have many
people who live together live today in
india who may not even be even aware of
the fact that they are
a descendant of whatever royal lineage
so royalty doesn't matter anymore in
india yeah we are now a
democracy of sorts who knows what will
be in the future maybe
maybe in 100 years india may be a
monarchy again who knows anything can
happen in the future
but uh yeah so that's the that's the way
it is today
right
um
boxing is the easiest way to get brain
damage there are many easier ways drink
a lot of alcohol you'll get brain damage
do drugs you'll get brain damage
you know
there are all kinds of ways of creating
getting brain damage boxing obviously is
one of the ways you get punched
sufficient enough number of times you'll
get concussions you'll get all kinds of
problems in the brain and all that yeah
so yes any combat sport in which you get
hit in the head
is
a shortcut
to
brain damage even certain sports like
cricket in which people can get hit on
the head they also can cause problems
and so on there is this australian
cricketer i forget his name
uh
he's a guy with a longish hair blonde
hair
will pukovsky or something he's had like
nearly 10 or maybe more than 10
concussions
it's a good batsman but you know it's
it's very hard for him to continue
playing because
i mean this is a significant thing of
what causes concern so yeah there are
many ways of getting brain damage most
sports are dangerous inherently yeah
well that's how it is i mean life
life is dangerous so why not play sports
but yeah boxing you have to be careful
certainly
that's why in in the amateur level you
wear those protective
stuff whatever it is on your head to
ensure that you don't hit too hard and
all that even that can
help you or safeguard you only to a
certain level
all right let's take some other
questions
yes this is a continuation on a theme
that i get almost every week akshay says
if india was so advanced
why are we so backward and superstitious
and illiterate well sir i am not
backward or superstitious or illiterate
but yeah if you want to talk about india
statistically on an average some people
could claim that india has all kinds of
problems
look at it this way my dear friends
uh
steve jobs created a company called
apple
yes
it was sometime in the 1980s 1970s
wherever it was
yeah so this gentleman steve jobs
created this company apple
and it came up with a number of personal
computers they made personal computers a
thing
they brought it into the public
consciousness that yeah we can all have
a computer of our own and use it for
some legitimate purpose genuine purpose
it's not some luxury so he created this
company which was doing very well
then
there was a political coup within
apple
and steve jobs was ousted from apple he
was thrown out right this is part of
history we know this
then for more than a decade if i'm not
mistaken steve jobs was not
a member of apple he was not involved
with apple he was out
during that period of time
apple's fortunes nose dived there was
new leadership new management
new ceo all that who engineered all this
and apple
it went from a highly profitable company
to a company that was on the verge of
bankruptcy in about a decade or so
slightly give or take plus or minus a
few years right
so tell me something tell me something
whom would you blame for the downturn in
fortunes of apple would you blame the
employees
or would you blame the leadership that
was in charge of the company whom do you
blame
do you blame the employees or do you
blame the leadership i think any sane
person would say it is the fault of the
leadership that everything went bad yes
now
let's come back to india
yes things went bad in the past 1000
years
who
was in charge of india who was deciding
the laws in the societal structure in
the societal class system and everything
who was in charge of india it was a
bunch of foreign occupiers and
colonizers starting with the turks and
ending with the europeans
they were in charge of every aspect
of life in india for a thousand years
and yes things went bad
lots of terrible things happened in
india society got distorted many uh
bad practices crept into society all
kinds of things went bad india became
extremely poor and so on and so forth
all kinds of ills in society whom will
you blame for these ills
the leadership and management or the
employees
will you blame the victims or will you
blame the actual oppressors
i hear this every day why are we so
backward why are these are this it is
all our fault it's all our fault the
problem is not
the the fault is not of the people who
ask the question
the fault is that of the education
system that does not tell you what has
been done to your ancestors
you have no idea of the unspeakable
horrors that were perpetrated on india
for 1000 years
and that's why you keep blaming
yourselves and your ancestors that
everything is our fault
who was the management who was the
leadership who was the ceo that was
running the company
why don't you ask yourselves that
wake up and ask the right questions
stop blaming the victims
for everything that went wrong
that is my simple message
to all of you
all right
uh let's let's uh
there we go dowry thank you thank you uh
thank you very much
all right all right all right
um
let's see some other interesting
questions
wtf act no something else no no i don't
know about that
uh
um
do we have any interesting questions
what if the british never ruled india
then india would be a different place
and like i said what if steve jobs was
never ousted from apple
apples would
have been a very different company
similarly what if the british never
ruled india well before the british were
the turks so they would have continued
i suppose unless they were
see the british they did not replace the
turks of course they replaced the
maratha empire
and the the maratha empire declined
because of infighting and politics and
and internal problems so the british
took advantage of that
so uh had the british never ruled india
either the marathas or their successors
would have been ruling india and india
would have been a much better place
or maybe some kind of combination of
turkic whatever so there are all kinds
of possibilities and these are all
hypotheticals
but what if you were to change the
question and ask a better question which
is what if the foreigners had never
ruled india
in that case india would have been a way
more advanced and better
uh subcontinent and civilization than
what it is today way more advanced
yes
so yeah that's what it is
uh shaheen says what are the origins of
chess and how has it evolved over time
the origins of chess lie in india i
think none of the historians who
typically like to distort in industry
even they are not able to dispute that
because we have found evidence of chess
boards
made out of rock
in the in i think western india
in the saraswati
uh region i think it was either in
lothal
or dholavira or something in western in
saurashtra gujarat that region yeah
so it's clear that chess is something
that evolved out of india in deep
antiquity if there were chess boards and
pieces made out of rock there would have
been chess boards and pieces made out of
wood also
much before that so we don't know when
it first emerged but it's something that
evolved deep in the antiquity of indian
civilization
and uh
later on i think the persians got hold
of it the chinese got hold of it and
they gave it various names
and then the europeans got hold of it it
was uh what was it called in india
i'm not sure what it was called in india
are the the persians they call it
shattaranj
and yeah that's that's the kind of story
it has i think you can look it up online
to find actual details of how the name
evolved how did the
the name of the sport become chess in
english i mean what made these
english-speaking people decide that we
will call it chess and not something
else there must have been some story
behind that i'm not i'm not quite
familiar with what the story is
even the ancient game of snakes and
ladders that also came out of india yeah
that's an indian origin game chess is an
indian origin game most likely kabaddi
that contact sport very physical sport
that also is an indian origin game and
as we know polo is also a game that
emerged out of india in out of manipur
so uh many of these ancient sports they
came out of india and if you look at the
story of lord krishna as in his
childhood playing with a bat and ball on
the on the banks of the river yamuna the
ball goes into the river and there's
there's this great snake sitting inside
and there's the whole episode around
that
well what game was he playing with the
baton ball
cricket or an ancient variant of cricket
so there you go many of these ports have
actually emerged out of india
right
let's see some other
oh
aditya kumar khar says in bengali we
call chess dhaba that's interesting
that's something i did not know i
learned something today
thank you for telling me that sir and
telling us all that
chaturanga yes sir
has given us the right answer chaturanga
it was called chaturanga in sanskrit
that's the original name of this
game
it's not chess it's chaturanga correct
sir thank you thank you i now that you
show it to me i i remember it thank you
appreciate it
uh
bobby says purchasy
could you elaborate some is that chess
because that's something i'm not this
this is a word i've not seen before
interesting interesting
um
the stoic berserker says why is japan's
birth rate
decreasing
and what's the cause of a lot of mental
problems in japan even if they are quite
advanced
see um
why is japan's birth rate decreasing
it's because the economy is not doing
well it has not been doing well since
the late 1980s the economy took a down
downhill turn it's been going downhill
ever since
and because of the shenanigans of the
bank of japan which is controlled by
foreign powers
uh things went bad you know uh they
played around with the interest rates
they played around with the value with
the uh value of the currency visa with
the dollar and so on and because of the
way they played with the interest rates
it became uh by raising the interest
rates uh
it it
it burst the uh property bubble in japan
first of all and then it made it very
unattractive for japanese people
to
to spend a lot to consume so consumption
went down that made the economy go
further down and so on and the cost of
living increase and so on so the overall
thing is that now
wages are not as high as they would have
been
as they used to be in the 80s
comparatively on a parity
perspective from a parity perspective
the wages are lower
uh
prices are high
and it's really really expensive to
raise children
and overall the society uh is not a
happy society
there are fewer children the overall
median age is increasing
um it's a more gloomy pessimistic
society it's see understand that this
country is under foreign occupation
it's been under foreign occupation since
1945.
for some time until the mid 80s the
economy was allowed to grow the japanese
people were allowed to
to uh
decide
their economic fortunes but then
something went wrong we don't know
we don't know who
is behind it and who made the decisions
and who forced whom to do what but this
is what happened so now consumption has
dropped even today there is very there
is much lower consumption than in the
1980s in japan so consumer behavior has
changed a lot
property prices are high
and there are all these problems so
that's why the birth rate is decreasing
it's very expensive to have kids and and
to raise kids
you know the other things and mental
problems yeah there are mental problems
that are i think it has a reasonably
high rate of suicide unfortunately japan
you have this unfortunate phenomenon of
of elderly people dying alone and not
that body is not been discovered for
days or weeks or months even yeah that
sort of thing
um you have this phenomenon of hikiko
mori which is
young people who never go out of their
house who live in their parents house
and stay inside their rooms for weeks or
months on end so there are all these
problems that exist in japan this is all
these are all symptoms of a society that
is unfortunately
not
allowed to determine its own fate
it's a society
that is under foreign occupation and a
foreign power
a foreign force
is guiding the fortunes of the society
and we are seeing that it's a society
that is
sadly sadly in decline and the
population is projected to go down
significantly in the next 100 years
which is which is actually
a tragedy altogether
okay um
why doesn't india create wasall states
in puppet governments you got to have
the strength and the power to do that
understand what power is
can you go and make a few wasall people
do you have the power to do it
think about it that way right
all right let's take some other
questions um
what is the biggest obstacle to bharat
growth the biggest obstacle to bharat's
growth is internal problems
internal problems
mental colonization and various
manifestations of foreign interference
in india's internal affairs and various
sections of indian society this
different disparate sections of indian
society that
not all but some of them definitely are
not working in india's interest yes
and
also this
big disunity that you have within india
there is a big sense of disunity within
india and let me give you an example
let me ask a question to all of you how
many indians
died during british occupation of india
the british occupation of india was
about two and a half three centuries yes
i will ask a simple question how many
indians do you think died now all of you
will give all kinds of different answers
some will say
5 lakhs some will say 10 million some
will say 15 million some say 30 million
some will say whatever
everybody will give different answers
nobody knows the truth
i will give you a figure of 100 million
and then a whole lot of people will
start arguing against me
so we can't even
agree on the most basic of things and
there is this sense
that your local region is more important
than the nation i'm not saying everybody
feels that way but there is a
significant sense of that so all of
these internal issues are the biggest
obstacle to india's growth and of course
there is the entire
nature of the indian administration
system government's
governance system the bureaucracy which
is colonial nature
the education system which is completely
colonial which continues
to perpetuate mental colonization there
is the problem of corruption which is a
huge drain on india's economy and so on
and so on so forth yeah
lots of problems but every problem can
be solved with the right leadership
and we are from the leadership
perspective we are definitely going in
the right direction so yes there are
problems but every problem has a
solution and every problem is an
opportunity to take the nation in the
right direction so i think india is
doing
reasonably well
and yeah we would like to see it
continue in the right direction
okay
okay what else do we have
um
many books defend churchill yeah we know
that
okay let's see this tanmay says there
are many books that defend churchill
saying that he actually wanted to
prevent the famine and even talked about
it in the assembly and all the things
all right
words or actions what is more important
he said he may i don't know what he said
he did not did not say but let's say
hypothetically
that he said he wanted to prevent a
famine
and let's say he went and spoke about it
in an assembly but what action did he
take
the actions he took
caused the famine
so who cares what he said
and who cares what he wanted
all that matters is what actions he took
who cares
the people of india
placed too much emphasis on words
and intentions oh he may have failed but
he had good intentions oh but he wrote
so many good things and he said that he
meant this
i don't give a damn about what somebody
said or what his or her intentions were
what actions did they take and what were
the consequences of the actions that is
the only yardstick by which you measure
the worth in the legacy of a leader
get that through your heads my dear
friends
it doesn't matter what somebody wrote
somebody may have wrote tens of
thousands of pages worth of wonderful
things
it doesn't matter
somebody may have given a million
wonderful speeches
somebody may actually have had good
intentions doesn't matter
all that matters is what actions did
they take and what were the consequences
of the actions that is the only
yardstick by which you measure a leader
and his or her
worth and value and legacy
simple keep things simple
so that is what i have to say about this
right
all right uh let us see
what else
what occupied the universe before the
big bang what is the universe occupying
as it expands
before
there is a certain amount
of
matter and energy within the universe
and that is what occupied the universe
at the moment of the big bang the
universe was a tiny infinitesimally
small
point like singularity or near to a
singularity and everything that's within
the universe was contained within that
so that's what occupied the universe at
the moment of the big bang we have no
idea
of what came before the big bang
you ask stephen hawking you ask albert
einstein
you ask whoever you want
they will give you the same answer we
don't know what came before the big bang
right
and the question the other question is
what is the universe occupying as it
expands we don't know what lies beyond
the universe
how do we know
we don't have any observational evidence
we only can see something within
whatever exists within the so-called
cosmological horizon
that is a bubble or a sphere with us at
the center and the diameter is about
billion light years we can only see what
is within that what's beyond that we
don't know there is a universe beyond
that as well we know that but we don't
know what lies there and beyond the
universe what lies we have absolutely no
idea we have no idea you can ask any
scientist you want you can ask nobel
prize winners you can ask anyone
there is no way for us to know we can
only reduce things based on
observational evidence yeah and we have
no observations of what's beyond the
universe so we have no evidence there
you go
[Music]
what do i think of stoicism
is it a good philosophy to follow and
practice so there is this famous book
called meditations
which was written by the roman emperor
marcus orillus yes
he is somebody that the fictional
representation of m is found in the
movie gladiator yes
so this guy was a
of
an adherent of this philosophy now what
do i think of it
i don't know what to think of it i've
never studied stoicism i have not
studied a single book on stoicism so i
don't know
people say it's great or to be a stoic
means to be somebody who doesn't speak
much yeah to be a quiet taciturn person
uh that appeals to me somewhat
uh you know me as somebody who speaks
non-stop but in real life i speak less
actually
compared to most people yeah so uh
that's uh what i could say i don't know
much about it i hear only good things
about stoicism
so maybe when i ever get the time i may
try and
crack a book open on stoicism maybe
marcus or releases book
meditations and maybe i will learn
something about it so uh yes i've heard
of it i'm aware of it i hear good things
about it but i personally have not
followed it i've not studied it and
so yeah that's the answer that is the
answer that i can offer you my dear
friends there are things that i have not
studied many things i have not studied
okay
money
says iran is way better than the kingdom
of saudi arabia although it has a
theocracy i find it more culturally
rooted and mature than the latter
the islamic republic of iran is far
better than the
gentlemen and ladies who are the desert
dwellers of kingdom of saudi arabia
let me offer you a different perspective
my dear friends
geopolitically
in the year 2022 which we are living in
i think yeah 22.
geopolitically india has far better
relations
with the kingdom of saudi arabia than
with iran
iran has never been a reliable
partner to india we have been requesting
the iranians a very small thing for
decades
send us a few cheetahs so that we can
reintroduce cheetahs in our in our land
they never did that
yeah
we have been trying to um
do oil exploration in the persian gulf
in in
their exclusive economic zone
in a way that's mutually beneficial to
both nations no
they have not allowed indian companies
to
uh to do this you know the farzad b gas
field and all that
in the 1965 war they allowed pakistan
to park their precious jet jet fighters
on iranian territory so that they can be
safeguarded from indian attacks yeah
iran has never been
in the past century maybe past five
centuries maybe past ten centuries any
kind of good friend of india not a good
friend of india
we are essentially the same people
indians and persians
the ancestors of the persians are
descendants of vedic clans yeah
we are essentially the same people
before the events of 1400 years ago
we had very similar cultures
yeah the language is also very similar
and yet
persia is not a reliable partner so uh
whatever value judgment i make is from
my
perspective from a geopolitical
perspective from a self from a narrow
self-interest perspective
and from that perspective i think the
kingdom of saudi arabia
is a better partner to india
than persia
that's how i see it
culturally rooted much mature and all
that yeah well
that's okay you can see everybody has
that perspective my perspective is
purely geopolitical the geopolitical
perspective is
who
can i rely upon with whom do i have
long-term
shared interests
and so on
there is the question of balochistan do
you know that iran occupies half of
balochistan
balochistan is occupied half
half of balochistan is occupied by
pakistan
and half is occupied by iran the balochi
people are not persians
they're indians
there you go so there are all these
matters you need to look at things from
a bigger perspective and from the narrow
lens of geopolitical self-interest and
then things look different so from my
perspective saudi arabia is better than
iran because they are cooperating with
us in
a host
of matters
whether it is energy security whether it
is actual national security and various
other things we are pretty much on the
same page in a multitude of matters
yeah
and look at the
look if you look at the overall attitude
of the new ruler d factor ruler of ksa
that is uh mr mohammed bin salman
he is pretty much
very positively
uh inclined and disposed towards india
that's good you cannot say the same of
the leadership in iran
so from my perspective we have better
long-term prospects
with the saudis than with iran
right
somebody has a crush on a girl good good
luck sir
uh
uh what else do we have how many indians
are in saudi i believe there are lots
and lots of indians in saudi arabia i
think there's a religious factor to that
most of them would be muslims obviously
uh and so many muslims are that i
suppose
so i don't have the exact figures in
front of me but i believe there must be
plenty of indians there
um
and nowadays indians are treated with
much more respect than they used to be
in the past so that's a that's a good
positive thing yeah overall
uh
what was it what was that
i missed a question somewhere it
disappeared
lots of questions are coming in that's
why it's hard for me to
hang on to questions anyway apologies
for that to whoever it was
um
yeah i get this question uh all the time
there was something called a sri yantra
of 13 by 13 miles square miles found in
oregon usa 1990 with pinpoint accuracy
isn't that a concrete evidence of aliens
can we recreate it with laser technology
from space it is a concrete evidence of
of human beings creating this thing
right i think there is an article in
which the people who created that
structure they actually came forth and
they showed how it was done in the past
i remember when i was a little kid there
was this phenomenon of crop circles so
initially there used to be this big
farmlands in which perfect circles would
appear some would be small some would be
significantly large some would be
gigantic they would appear overnight
the previous day there was nothing there
the morning you find a big crop circle
and you can see the full scale of that
from the air from helicopters and planes
and over time the complexity of these
crop circles got mind-boggling let me
show you an image of a crop circle shall
we let's put that on the screen
props
circle
let's put that on the screen let me
share my image so these crop circles
started appearing
typically in england in the uk
later in the us and the geometrical
shapes were mind-boggling they started
increasing in complexity can you look at
can you see this can you see how complex
this is
this is all something that was done by
people
they would do this overnight and they
found ways and techniques of doing it
very intricate geometric shapes
very difficult to create and they would
do it in a matter of hours in the middle
of the night
right
so these are various crop circles all
kinds of complex geometrical images
and beautiful images you know
and similar to this sri yantra oregon
sri
[Music]
yantra oregon
oregon right
so that's something similar to that
and i think this was done by people
and the people who actually created this
they did come forward and they admitted
that they did this so there is nothing
supernatural there is nothing alien to
it
uh people like to believe it because
there is some because this is a
apparently something to do with the
indian culture perhaps i'm not sure okay
i i lack a knowledge of what the sri
yantra is
it looks like the various buddhist
mandalas
ancient
dharmic mandala structures and all that
it looks like that so yeah somebody
decided to recreate that
i'm not sure how long it took for them
to do it if it is 13 square miles it
would have taken them much more than one
night but it's in the middle of the
desert so maybe nobody noticed them
doing doing this
so it's got a very simple explanation it
was done by people
not by aliens right
laser tech from space i don't think the
technology exists thus far right to do
that
okay um
what else do we have
why doesn't the government accept gum
nami baba wasabashin rabos well it's for
the government to give the answer
uh there seems to be very very strong
evidence
that
himself there seems to be very strong
evidence in favor of that but well
the government will have its priorities
and prerogatives and maybe um
i think the government should answer
that question if they ever will yeah
okay
um
why do you love the best prime minister
india has ever had that is mr nehru so
much i mean you answered the question he
was the best best
he was the best prime minister india has
ever had
the best there ever was the best there
ever is the best that ever will be like
bret hart
so if somebody is that best and that
great we have to love him isn't it
it is our duty
to
pay sufficient adequate respect to
shrink and respect him adequately
okay
a purver says
according to uh the external affairs
minister joshua ankurji the british
looted 43 trillion dollars worth of uh
blunder from india yet today their
economy is just over 3.3 trillion
dollars worth where do you think the
remaining dollars went
good question good question
uh it's actually 45.
so that's what various economists have
calculated based on whatever evidence
and data is available in the public
domain i think it must be more than that
because much of this much of the loot
would never have been documented but
yeah let's let's take the figure of 45
trillion dollars from india
today
britain's economy the uk's economy is
3.3 trillion dollars and ours has
surpassed that
what does it mean
that a nation's gdp
is 3.3 trillion dollars it means
that in one year
it produces an economic output
of 3.3 trillion dollars
per year
india's economic output per year is now
what 3.5 3.6 trillion dollars it's per
year only
think about it
the shri padmanabaswamy temple has a
massive
amount of treasure stored within it
which
whose value
is well in excess of a trillion dollars
and there are vaults that have not even
been opened thus far
yeah
so that itself is more than a third of
the entire indian economy
it's not the economy it's just one
year's output gdp output
so britain's
yearly
gdp
is 3.3 trillion dollars but if you were
to do a valuation
of all the land of all the properties of
all that is valuable in the uk that
would be well in excess
of 3.3 trillion dollars
well in excess of that maybe 10 times
maybe 100 times of that
but the annual economic output is 3.3
trillion dollars that's the difference
so what they plundered out of india
would have been worth at least 45
trillion dollars in today's money i
think it would be much much more than
that
all right so that's the difference
and much of the money
was dissipated
it's not all all that treasure
it was
it was transformed
in other forms of of value
and many of the families that hoarded
that looted the wealth some of them they
went and settled down in the u.s some of
them would have descendants who are in
various parts of europe so the wealth
was over time redistributed
why is the uk so prosperous what do they
produce they produce nothing
and yet they are so prosperous it's all
built upon the wealth plundered out of
india and the rest of europe which again
doesn't produce that much it is that
incredibly prosperous because of all the
wealth that was plundered out of south
america out of africa and also out of
india
so that's how the west has become
prosperous and why is the west declining
today
because they actually don't produce much
there you go
so yeah that's the answer i hope that
makes sense
right let's see something people are
putting all kinds of
emojis and all
uh you got to ask good questions my dear
friends ask me good questions
ask me the kind of question that i just
can't resist answering ask me that
uh where are we 60 including france
portugal denmark netherlands so many so
many countries that all came to india
to plunder india
to plunder india you know people say
india has been a poor nation and we all
came here to whatever why do you think
everybody was making a bee line to come
to india
did all of these european nations want
to come to india to to do charity in
india
no
geopolitics is all about self-interest
there was something they wanted from
india
india was the most
prosperous and wealthy
place on the surface of the planet
that's why all these europeans once they
discovered navigation and all that
that's why they all started coming to
india understand that
okay one she says that the national
wealth of the uk is 15 trillion dollars
okay i have not uh verified this but
let's say it is so yeah there you go it
makes sense yep
if if you look at all the land in
australia for instance
i think the total valuation would be
around four or five or six
maybe six or seven
trillion
dollars the entire land of australia if
you were to put a value on that
based on real estate property prices
maybe it's around that
so the uk is much smaller so yeah maybe
maybe this makes sense yeah
so that's the difference between your
annual gdp and your actual national
wealth or valuation
right
are the questions
prana pranam says have you read a manga
called berserk
which has magnificent art it is one of
the best fictions ever written
unfortunately i have not read the manga
called berserk i've heard about
something called berserk it's about
vikings is it vikings and stuff like
that
maybe but i haven't read it but i think
i've heard that manga is very
interesting and lots of people are into
it and uh the
natural
uh outcome of manga
is is enemy right japanese enemy that
also seems to be very popular i no
longer have the time to
indulge indulge in these pleasures but
yeah
i'm sure it's great
uh
okay
this is by ali i'm person from iran
greetings sir greetings dear cousin
i know us in indians are cousins in some
videos you claim that we came from india
why it took us so much time to build an
empire when we had knowledge of indians
um
see when we don't know exactly when the
events of the battle of the ten kings
happened it was more than ten kings it
was a geopolitical struggle that has a
long story behind it but it happened at
the very beginning of the vedic age or
maybe just before the vedic age because
it's already written about in the
rigveda now when did the vedic age
happen
there is no consensus
but i would say it would have happened
closer to 6000 bc when the great river
saraswati was still in its prime
so
if it happened let's say hypothetically
around 5000 bc which is 7000 years
before today then the exodus
of the various uh
clans rigby clans
that lost the battle would have happened
around 7000 years ago and that's
whatever what would have uh spread
indo-european genetics and linguistics
all across eurasia westwards out of the
indian subcontinent
so let's say that the pursue the parshwa
people
migrated out of india westwards into
present day persia about 7 000 or so
years ago then maybe they would have
settled down there and maybe it took
time for them
to become powerful enough and to develop
this this
uh imperial outlook
and or build an empire
we know that there were dynasties that
predate
the accommodate dynasty so there are
very dinosaurs that came before the
community dynasty too they would have
had their own kings and kingdoms and all
that but
until the accommodate dynasty
accompanies the energy of shamanic
dynasty it was never an empire
portia never had an imperial outlook
before that
it takes times empires rise and fall if
you look at the history of india empires
rise and fall rise and fall rise and
fall
once typically every 500 or so years
yeah
so maybe there would have been
significant dynasties before the
accommodate dynasty maybe there would
have been empires uh we know that we had
the medians
we know that you had we know that there
was the
the marhashi kingdom in
southern persia
about
four and a half thousand or so years
before today so they also the maharishi
maharashtra kingdom etc would also have
been the predecessors of the accommodate
dynasty and so on so
there must have been empires
before
the accommodate dynasty but i don't
think any of them were at the scale they
have the kind of scale of conquest that
the
uh accommodate dynasty had and the
cabinet dynasty almost exclusively
expanded westwards it was always west
west west fight the the greeks first
then fight the romans and and conquer
their territories so clearly there was a
there was this
uh policy of not trying to invade india
always go westwards so that kind of
tells you that there was
some kind of understanding between india
various indian kingdoms and the persians
and of course we know that the persian
empire the accommodation empire
used
battle elephants now elephants don't
uh
are not found in persia right they are
found in india so they would have
acquired these war elephants from
indians
which tells you that there would have
been good
diplomatic relations between the persian
empire and whichever empire was ruling
india or whichever kingdoms were ruling
india at the time so yeah it's it's uh
much of this
much of the events of the past uh four
or five thousand years are lost
whatever we know is mainly through
european eyes and sources
the greeks and
all that yeah because even when it comes
to the persian empire it was destroyed
by this
by uh
alexander the greek this barbaric
warlord who came and it burned down this
beautiful
beautiful city of parshvapur persepolis
and the fire consumed the whole city you
can still see uh traces of that fire
today in the ruins of purse police
so yeah most of what we understand about
persia and india is through western
sources and that's why we don't quite
know the full
history
so yeah that's what i can say about this
but uh great to hear from you ali
okay looks like we have not done any
video chat today so yeah maybe maybe
maybe next time perhaps perhaps
um
yes yes swapna cheetahs are finally in
i'm very happy to see that and may they
grow and may they prosper and may they
multiply
um what next what next do we have
i can see certain
funny comments ah what about this paul
chohan says why is the tamil and
cameroonian language so similar well i
don't know tamil
and neither do i know the community
language so i don't know
yeah i hear all kinds of
claims that are made that
tamil is similar to korean tamil is
similar to japanese tamil is similar to
the various african languages
essentially tamil is similar to
everything
so some of that may actually be true
okay i'm not trying to trying to make
fun of anything
but i personally know nothing about this
maybe someday i should learn tamil and
then
maybe learn korean maybe learn
cameroonian and then thereby expand my
linguistic horizons and then maybe i
will be able to answer such questions
but thus far i am sadly not
sufficiently informed about this
[Laughter]
okay let me take this i have answered
some questions so many times but anyway
could you please tell us why the indus
valley civilization got destroyed are
there any theories
have you seen any evidence of
destruction
when you say destroyed it means
destruction do you see any evidence of
bomb blasts do you see any evidence of
buildings blown apart do you see any
evidence of buildings hammered to pieces
do you see any evidence of battles do
you see any evidence of fire do you see
any evidence of ashes on in any of the
archaeological strata do you see any
evidence of
of
axes and arrowheads
or swords do you see any evidence of
dead bodies with
sword wounds or or arrow wounds or
anything you see none of that
anywhere
not a single evidence of that
so how can you say the indus valley
civilization was destroyed
how do you make the claim
think think logically
there is no evidence for any destruction
so here's what happened
the great river saraswati started drying
out about 3 4 000
bc
the decline of this great river started
around 6000 bc when the indian monsoon
started
declining
monotonically which means very slow very
gradual decline
but this great river the saraswati was a
rain-fed monsoon fed river in its upper
reaches up north
it took in some glacial melt water from
the himalayan glaciers and snows
but the majority of the water of this
river came from the indian monsoon it
was a massive river almost entirely rain
fed and because the monsoon declined
gradually but by about 1500 bc it was a
very steep decline of the monsoon and
that's why
by around 1500 bc the great river mostly
disappeared
and some parts of it are still
extinct today it is called the
river so because of climate change
the entire climate of the region changed
got transformed look at balochistan
today it's desert
look at western pakistan even parts of
sindh it's deserted look at the thar
region of india
rajasthan it's desert this was all green
and lush
in the old days so because of climate
change because of the entire because of
the transformation and complete change
of the sun region
that's why
many of these archaeological sites that
were built around on the banks of the
saraswati had to be abandoned india is a
river valley civilization
the indian subcontinent is full of
rivers it is so
rich and fertile and full of rivers
that the whole of indian civilization is
a riverbed civilization all of india's
great settlements and cities
are built on the banks of rivers kashi
think of kashi think of the ganga
valley region the yamuna valley region
narmada valley region the godavari
valley region the kaveri valley region
river after river after river everything
is built on the banks of rivers
so because of climate change
the saraswati disappeared
and that's why and the other rivers were
also affected significantly
they must have been much stronger in the
past much more powerful and much more
yeah voluminous in the past so because
of climate change over a period of many
centuries these settlements in the
saraswati hindu region were slowly and
gradually
abandoned the people had to abandon them
slowly and gradually over a course of
multiple centuries and these people most
of them went and settled down eastwards
in the ganga yamuna valley region in the
narmada valley region up north in
northern india some of them would have
even gone westwards west of india
so that is what happened there was no
destruction whatsoever it was a gradual
abandonment
of the region especially the saraswati
valley because of the effects of climate
change that is what happened and i have
written about this i have spoken about
this you can google it a widget chard
are invasion theory and you will find
evidence and links to various papers
that that have
uh studied the studied what happened
here right so that is what happened it
was not destroyed it was gradually
abandoned and the people of the
saraswati hindu civilization
they still exist
their descendants still exist it is you
and me and all indians
the civilization never went anywhere
it still exists
so the so-called indus valley
civilization
or the so-called harappan civilization
is merely a small phase of indian
civilization which has a history
unbroken history of more than nine and a
half thousand years
indian civilization has an unbroken
cultural continuum of almost 10 000 or
more than that yes the best
archaeological evidence is about the
earliest archaeological evidence goes
back to about nine and a half thousand
years before today
so indian civilization has existed
existed continuously for nine and a half
thousand years and the indus valley
phase was just one
phase of the entire history it's not
some separate civilization it's not some
separate people who disappeared
please understand that
okay
so we are uh nearing the two hour mark
so let's take
some more questions
uh what did i say
what makes a question a good question
this is a good question this is a good
question what makes a question a good
question it's something that
by
it's a question by answer
if i answer the question
it will
um
help a lot of people
yeah
so a question that whose answer helps a
lot of people and enhances their
knowledge and adds to the to their
knowledge that is a good question
so
and and it's some hopefully it's
something that i have not answered 75
times before
so that is my rough working definition
of a good question typically it's
something that catches my eye and i say
i think that yes this is something i
need to answer and this is something
that will help everybody yeah
so that's my
my working definition of a good question
yeah
right um
peter parker no no no
somebody else somebody else um
amrush prince says why were the american
colonies colonists who were less
populous and inferior able to defeat the
british in the american revolution but
india was not able to succeed the
american colonists
are the same people as the british they
had the same language the same know-how
of battle and war tactics and they had
the same weapons but they had the added
advantage of having access to the
resources of the north american
continent
and they were able to use that and the
enormous
strategic advantage it gave them
to fight the british the british
eventually had to depend on supplies
coming in across the atlantic
and so you know these are the factors
that allowed
the american colonists to defeat the
british it was it was not something that
happened overnight it took several years
but they were sufficiently well
motivated
the motivation was that we will no
longer have to pay taxes to the british
crown we will be able
to uh keep everything for ourselves
whatever we are plundering out of this
new land that we have captured
so yeah uh to understand this in proper
detail you have to actually study the
the
history of the american revolutionary
war but overall these are the factors
that contributed to that
so yeah this is a good question
see history is about cause and effect
understand this
history is about cause and effect if you
are if you want to truly study history
properly and to truly understand history
you have to understand that history is
about causality it's about the causal
chain
the cause and effect chain
everything that exists today
is the consequence
of decisions that were taken
5000 years ago 10 000 years ago 70 000
years ago if a decision was taken
differently at that time
the two days that we are experiencing
would not exist
there is a causal chain
a cause and effect chain that connects
us to our earliest ancestors that
existed 20 million years ago or maybe
even before that
so this the true
study of history is the study of
causality
why do things happen and why do they
happen the way they happen
that is the true study of history it's
history it's not about memorizing dates
and memorizing the names of kings the
lists of kings and what happened when
it's about understanding why these
things happened
what caused this to happen why did this
happen and not that happen
why did this
king
succeed in conquering that place and why
did he want to conquer that place in the
first place
you to understand human nature
understand human psychology understand
causality that is what the true study of
history is about
all right let's take a couple more
questions
someone says can we bring back ma
saraswati well ma saraswati will come
back if she wants to return who are we
to force her to return she left for some
reason respect her will yeah there are
these various politicians who want to
recreate the saraswati by diverting god
knows what come on stop it
the river disappeared for a reason
if she wants to reappear if you consider
her to be a goddess if you consider the
river to be a manifestation of the great
divine master asparty then you have to
respect her wishes and stop trying to
re-engineer the river back into life
it is a natural phenomenon
yeah the river disappeared maybe it will
reappear someday in the future when the
time is right
right what else do we have do we have
other interesting questions i am sure
there are thousands of interesting
questions
all i know so it says so what do you
believe india's approach to be like
about what my dear friend
what's the question
are they ask a good question man give
some context
what should india's approach be about
what about rock and roll
about the art of playing tabla
about hockey
what cricket
about scuba diving what are you talking
about sir please give some context
so this is an example of a bad question
unfortunately i don't mean to
demean anybody but yeah there you go
okay okay okay okay let's take some good
question
some interesting question
now some people are trolling me by
asking the repeated same thing anyway
what the languages do you know
uh
i know multiple languages
the interesting ones i know some
sanskrit i know some latin i know
i know french
and i know a bunch of various i
understand bits and pieces and parts of
various
uh
western european languages especially
romance languages
that are descendants of latin
i
i know bits and pieces of lots of
languages you know
yes
it kind of helps sometimes yeah
okay let's take one final question
for today
seven thank you very much sir
uh
what do we have what do you have
mesopotamia etc we have spoken about
that
um
[Music]
let's see let's see do we have anything
that i can take as the last question
um
himanshu says south indian kingdoms used
to have maritime relationship with rome
why is it considered that vasco da gama
found the maritime route to india it is
the europeans who make the claim the
entire world history is written from an
accident occidentalist eurocentric
perspective
yeah
that's not the this this is not true i
mean the the the claim that da gama
discovered the maritime route to india
is it's nonsense
indians knew these rules for the longest
time
yeah maybe it was the first european in
the past
whatever 500 years to rediscover the
road to india but
he we don't have to
we don't have to see the world through
their lenses and their eyes
india had maritime relations with
here's here's an interesting tidbit in
case you you haven't already heard it
from me
uh if you look at the australian the
native australian population the
so-called aboriginal australian
population approximately if you look at
the statistical entirety of the native
australian population about 10 percent
of the genetics has comes from india
we know
archaeologists know and geneticists know
that about 5 000 years before today
there was a migration from from india
into australia
and those indians who went there left
behind their genetic imprint it is still
found today approximately 10 percent of
native australian genetics are of indian
origin so indians traveled to australia
by sea five thousand years ago
so indians knew how to make
incredibly difficult and long journeys
by sea indians
we know that zebu cattle entered egypt
entered africa at least four thousand
years before today
and india had trade relations with egypt
with uh greece
with rome for the longest time
indian ships is to go there so um
india is the oldest maritime
civilization in the world india was a
great maritime civilization india had a
great maritime tradition indians were
the finest shipbuilders in the world you
can see
sculptures on the walls of the angkor
wat temple
in
cambodia
which show indian ships the rig veda
mentions ships with a hundred oars yeah
so understand this india is the
had an incredibly
rich
and great maritime history today we are
taught that indians had this thing that
if you cross the ocean then you you you
i don't know you are cursed or something
that there is something that must have
occurred very recently
our ancestors used to go everywhere in
the world by sea by ship
yeah so that's the deal that is the deal
my dear friends my dear friends that's
the deal now do we have one last
question i can take
am i proud of the denisovan ancestry
that distinguishes indians from all
non-africans could genomic research in
andaman islanders change something
significant about human evolution
uh do indians have dinner someone
ancestry i'm not sure in case we have it
we should be proud of it in case we
don't have it we should still be proud
of it we should be proud of whatever
ancestry we have
okay
be proud of who you are be proud of your
ancestry be proud of your ancestors who
have done so much to ensure that you are
here uh genetic ins research in andaman
islanders it will definitely uh help us
understand the history and the story of
humanity better because they are a relic
population an isolated population
they've been isolated isolated for
30 000 plus years so yeah it's
interesting but we should treat them
with compassion
they are still essentially a stone age
people we should treat them with
compassion and with dignity and with
humanity we should not use them as
guinea pigs and test subjects which is
what europeans have always tended to do
we are not europeans we are indians we
are a separate civilization we have our
own values
and we should
use that
anyhow that brings me to the end of
today's session great fun great fun
doing this live chat session once again
thank you to everybody who asked
questions apologies to those of you who
have asked so many questions and i could
not take them i can only take 20 30
questions in these two hours
so apologies to those of you whose
question i did not either see or do not
take
i appreciate every single one of you i
appreciate your
viewership i appreciate the fact that
you trust me and ask me questions and we
will do this again this was fun again so
let's do a few live chat questions uh
sessions again in the future
so uh until then thank you very much i
will see you in tomorrow's session which
is going to be about geopolitics and
history mostly and current affairs until
then take care
and good night see you in the next
episode